I haven't spiraled yet and I'm pretty
old just make it a few more years and
you'll be
good I'm just running out the clock
now I'm Angela Duckworth I'm Steven
Dubner and you're listening to no stupid
questions today on the show is it
immoral to slack off at work when others
are depending on you to do a good job I
had a tiny bit of authority as an Umpire
of a minor Little League game and I
exploited it for my own benefit
also how valuable is it to have a
personal mission statement that sounds
like a marketing scam I can sell you one
and it comes with a set of steak
knives Angela Duckworth I have what may
be a truly stupid question but this is
the one place I'm allowed to ask it
that's right so here it goes do you
believe as I do that incompetence is
often a form of dishonesty and I can
spell out further what I mean by that if
you'd like I have first intuition which
is no but why don't you elaborate a
little bit yeah okay so I realize it's a
murky question but what I'm suggesting
is this I have encountered a lot of
people who consider themselves good
people moral and righteous and
pro-social and so on who happen to be
not very good at what they do
professionally so their work can be
sloppy or careless or they don't try
very hard to improve they don't get
upset when they mess up which irrit Ates
me I was going to say that upsets you
most probably it does it does and you
know I guess the biggest factor is they
don't consider how their actions affect
other people in that work sphere so I
used to think this was just Garden
variety incompetence that they were
doing their best but they just weren't
very good but over the years I've come
to think that most people are capable of
doing better but for whatever reason
they don't and my impression is that
they consider it less important to be
competent in their professional sphere
because in their daily personal lives
they are good and ethical people so I've
come to feel in some cases that
incompetence is a form of dishonesty
that these people are essentially
stealing time from their co-workers who
have to clean up their messes they're
degrading the shared Enterprise of work
that others are putting a lot of effort
into so what do you think am I a monster
for thinking this or is there some
validity well I hope that was
therapeutic For You Stephen just
expressing all of that I feel great
thanks I'm done see you later I think I
Now understand the question better you
see incompetence of the sort that did
sloppy work not trying your best Etc as
something which is harmful to others
yeah and that there's agency that
there's a choice that it's not really
trying your best but in fact some
volitional decision to not get things
done on time or not bring things to a
standard of Excellence that the person
could have done is that right first
first of all if I ever start a punk band
volitional decision is my
name uh yeah you as always boiled it
down beautifully much shorter and much
more on point so yes that's my issue
that there is a matter of volition but
volition needs to include a conscious
decision to care less about the quality
in a realm where others do overtly care
okay fair enough and at the core of both
incompetence and dishonesty is a sort of
selfishness like this is good for me I
know it's bad for you but because it's
good for me I'm going to do it anyway so
I can see why you're asking the question
now better than I first did because my
first intuition was like no let's go
into the next question but I think the
argument turns on whether people who are
not doing work that's up to your
standard are by and large doing it
because they feel licensed to try less
hard since they're trying so so hard in
other Realms of their life and I don't
know that that describes the
incompetence that I've seen it is true
though that people do occasionally feel
like there's some kind of sum of
goodness that they have to get to and
like if you tell three truths and it
allows you to tell one lie right I mean
do you really feel like people who are
kind of taking it easy and doing not as
great don't you think it's often because
they don't even see the problem that
they're not consciously aware that they
are at all
substandard so that is a good and
important question my guess is that most
people know I guess one reason I didn't
enjoy so much the jobs I had in in
journalism is I don't like being overly
dependent on others input when I care a
lot about the quality so I guess what
I'm describing as a control freak I know
what you mean and I think it's like
caring so much and I think it probably
irritates or something a little stronger
than irritation to feel like other
people are not caring as much yes right
yes in fact I sometimes discuss with my
Freakonomics radio producing partner
Allison krao like one of the single most
important characteristics that I really
need someone to have to be a useful
member of our team is that they have to
really really really hate to screw up
and if they don't hate it if it doesn't
burn them and keep them up and because I
screw up all the time I mean everybody
does so my rule of thumb is every time I
screw up I try to take it apart learn
from it and find a way to eliminate that
kind of mistake again yeah I mean for
you and me we actually don't have a
problem being like Oh I feel bad that I
made that mistake and then we without a
lot of emotional charge set about trying
to understand why we made the mistake
and trying not to do it again I think
what often happens though is that
there's a spiral of anxiety and kind of
I'm a bad person I think this happens a
lot to some people you know while you
were saying that I actually had like a
memory flash of a traumatic not really
traumatic a dramatic at least a really
negative event from adolescence and I
think about it still pretty routinely
whenever I'm about to be lazy or do
something stupid or whatnot so I played
baseball as a kid and I think I was in
Little League still but then they had
the minor Little League the little kids
and I was umpiring and you got paid like
a150 so it was awesome it's a lot of
money there was a rule that the games
had to go a certain number of innings to
be quote official but it was like two or
three Innings cuz they're really little
kids or until dark and for some reason
on this night I just was like feeling so
lazy or irresponsible or whatever that
even though the sun was still very high
in the sky after the requisite number of
innings I said okay that's it the G's
over you called it yeah I had a tiny bit
of authority as an Umpire of a minor
Little League game and I exploited it
for my own benefit because I just wanted
to get out of there get my $150 and go
buy candy with it and I got called out
on it later by the guy who ran the
league and he did it in a very nice way
and that made me feel even worse what
did he say he said listen you're right
that you do have the authority to call a
game after a certain number of innings
but the whole point of that is about
beating Darkness I remember he put it
back on me he said as you remember from
playing in the miners this is a
highlight of their week they love to
come here and then to take something
away that they're expecting is a real
sadness and I felt terrible and so to
this day whenever I think about like not
giving something the proper amount of
attention or effort that incident Cycles
through my subconscious and the horrible
feeling I had of guilt essentially and
shame makes me push a little bit harder
but you don't spiral right so you feel a
twinge or more of guilt or shame when
you fall short of a moral standard or
performance standard but you don't seem
to me like somebody who spirals then and
then like can't get Beyond it I haven't
spiraled yet and I'm pretty old just
make it a few more years and you'll be
good I'm just running out the clock now
no I haven't but I can see where it's a
powerful emotion powerful construct and
so now I feel bad about being the guy
who said a little while ago that like
people should hate to screw up more it's
good for you I do sound like a monster
you grew even in the course of one
conversation
no I think if we can learn to feel bad
but not feel too bad but look I believe
in caring and I think that's where this
all started right like you would like
people to care about their moral
standards and about their performance
standards and I don't think that's a bad
thing yeah you know what drives me crazy
is when someone did something wrong or
totally forgot to do it or sent the
wrong file to the wrong person and
they're like oh no problem here you go
and I'm like no it is a little bit of a
problem and that's what I mean by
treating competence as a form of honesty
maybe if I'd framed it that way rather
than the two negatives do you think that
competence is a form of honesty yeah I
mean what competence and honesty have in
common is that there is a standard and
there is integrity that it matters
whether I reach the standard or if I
fall short the thing I would want to say
as a psychologist is that most people
don't actually go to bed at night and
think I was incompetent nor do they go
to bed at night and think that they were
dishonest and actually when you look at
research on honesty and dishonesty
people have almost an infinite number of
ways to rationalize what they did so
that when they go to bed at night they
feel like oh I did my best and maybe it
was a little bit of a lie but it was a
Justified lie and they they might not
even use the word lie when they put
themselves to bed at night so I think
one question is what is really the
failure is it the failure to care about
not reaching standard or is it much
deeper than that and I I suspect it's
deeper than that that's why it's so hard
to change you're saying it's more a
failure of awareness then yeah I think
in many cases there's a a failure of
awareness or a kind of subterfuge like
we're faking out our own St because
nobody wants to go to bed thinking that
they're dishonest or incapable and so
it's much easier to create some account
for what we did and what we said and how
we conducted ourselves where we can go
to bed and still be the good guy tell me
a little bit more about moral licensing
which you've hinted at and it's
something that we've looked at on a few
Freakonomics radio episodes in the past
the was a nice experiment done by John
list and they basically found that if
people feel like they're doing good work
they're willing to take license in other
areas in other words be a little bit
either slack or dishonest so I'm curious
how strong the literature is in
Psychology and whether this idea of
moral licensing is truly a real and
Universal thing yeah I'm not an expert
in moral licensing but my read of the
research is that it is a real thing it's
part of a broader psychological
phenomenon which is this idea that we
can license ourselves to do something
which is inconsistent with our
principles because we feel like we got
credit earlier I mean to me the most
accessible example is you go to a fast
food restaurant and because you order a
Diet Coke you get the super sized fries
like well look I saved you know 150
calories on the soda so now I'm going to
get this 450 calorie salty potato snack
so the human mind is quite prone to
thinking that look nobody's perfect so
I'm just trying to get to a certain
number of good acts and if like I've
kind of done that in one way I don't
have to do it now that I've already
reached my threshold and maybe that
accounts for both incompetence to some
extent like this is good enough and also
maybe dishonesty you can imagine that
this could drive both of these irksome
not great behaviors you took all the
romance out of french fries by the way
450 calorie salty potato snack yeah so
can you tell us another example or two
about moral licensing like I seem to
recall having read things about racial
attitudes if people do a certain thing
or give a certain answer in one realm
that shows them to be kind of racially
enlightened or racially fair that they
will basically Pat themselves on the
back and that a subsequent action might
actually be in the opposite direction
yeah I mean I think that makes it sound
quite simple right that when we do a
good act then it kind of puts money in
our virtue bank and then we can you know
spend it a little bit later there was a
metaanalysis that I read that is a study
of studies and in this case there had
been 91 different studies of moral
licensing and in this metaanalysis
Stephen there was a small effect it
wasn't a sledgehammer effect the problem
is that the published studies had bigger
effect effect than the unpublished
studies and that always makes you wonder
whether file drawers are just
overflowing with n it's really nothing
my guess is that there is something
there but it could be really small and
there's so many other things that drive
human behavior we probably all have some
licensing going on below our conscious
awareness but we also have other things
going on below and above our conscious
awareness and maybe the moral here is
that we should be aware of that
dependenc because the desirable thing is
to have a standard reflect on that
standard and then to apply that standard
to All Occasions in your life and not
feel like you're getting to a a score
and then beyond that you know it's good
enough I mean satisficing is really not
a great way to approach
morality okay so let's say that I want
to be as what sounds like impossibly
self-aware as you just described because
that's hard but let's say want to be
aware of this tendency I want to address
it try to understand where it's coming
from and if I deviate try to fix it
somehow do you have any advice for that
you know Max baserman who is a
behavioral scientist that we both know
has recently been writing about this I
think his term for it is better not
perfect and I think when you set out
Perfection as the ideal then it actually
maybe paradoxically gets us to be less
moral because we think I'll never do
that and then you just you you know to
hell with it and so better is a better
goal than perfect and if you are always
striving to be better if you were in
that mindset I think you might be less
likely to morally license because you
wouldn't take this next occasion to tell
a little bit of a lie or take someone
else's time because you're always trying
to do better I don't know that sounds a
little polyana to me but I mean one of
my recent like oh my gosh this must
explain everything about human nature um
theories is that attention is so limited
and one of the problems with
incompetence dishonesty and so many
other problems is that our attention is
so selective and we can just ignore so
much let me ask you one last thing it
strikes me and again I may be wrong but
that just about everyone wants to appear
to be moral right yeah very few people
seem to want to be considered immoral or
even aoral has anyone ever done a good
job measuring the gap of De Ed morality
and actual morality you know I don't
know one of the most influential
psychologists when I was in school was a
guy named John sabini who felt like
what's really going on here is that
people want to feel like they're good
capable human beings and their desire to
do that can warp things can make them
oblivious to things and they just change
the narrative like oh well the reason I
had to steal that thing is cuz the
system is corrupt and therefore it was a
good thing that I stole that thing so I
do think the desire is very strong I
don't know if anybody has measured the
Gap to do that of course you would have
to have some measure of actual moral
Behavior it would be very hard to do in
the real world well as with so many
things that we most care about so many
behaviors and attitudes and so on we
really really want to see them in the
wild and not in the lab and the lab
really I mean no offense to you in your
field it isn't great at measuring and
analyzing
complicated behaviors yeah I mean almost
by definition right cuz when you bring
something into the lab you create some
little circumstance this situation but
that makes it very oversimplified you
know there was one field study of
morality the wallet test where I think
it was something like 177,000 wallets
were left in all different parts of the
world and then it was just observed like
what do people do when they find a
wallet most people are honest that was
one of the conclusions of the study not
everyone so you could begin at least to
try to get out of the lab and ask the
question for example whether the people
who were encountering these wallets
considered themselves to be honest
people and then you could see whether
they really did or didn't return the
wallet to the owner or try well going
back to the question I asked about
incompetence as a form of dishonesty now
that you've told me that most of us see
ourselves as good and wanting to be seen
as good I feel I put myself in the
minority there of like I care much less
about people and more about not sucking
so if nothing else I've established
bonafides that I don't always go with
the crowd actually probably one reasons
I like you I think that you are not one
to be checking with what everybody else
thinks first before you decide what you
think right but I mean hopefully one of
the few things that you'd like to be
with the crow on is like wanting to
appear to be a good person I'm sure you
have that I don't think you go to bed at
night think you're not a good person
either I don't you don't go to bed
thinking I'm not a good person or you
don't go to bed thinking I don't go to
bed thinking that in other words I'm
guilty of probably rationalizing all
kinds of little things and ignoring lots
of things that I would like to ignore
but I'm just saying that I sure you do
the same thing cuz you know it's human
nature you know I think the moral of the
story is not to go to bed at
night still to come on no stupid
questions Angela and Steven debate the
value of top level personal goals how
about every day try to suck a little bit
less
[Music]
yeah Stephen I'm curious whether you
have a top level goal
what it's a simple yes or no question
that sounds like a marketing scam cuz I
can sell you one and it comes with a set
of steak
knives did you know that Andrew Yang
former presidential candidate was was a
Cutco knife salesman early in his career
I did not know that it is true so wait
do I have a top level goal you're asking
me so you know okay first of all I have
to say I feel like you and I are pretty
good friends we are pretty good friends
I think but I feel the fact that you're
asking me if I have a top level goal
infers you don't know me at all because
you have no idea what I'm talking about
because of course you have one cuz I
definitely don't have any idea what
you're talking about and I'm almost sure
that I don't have a top level goal oh no
hold on let me explain what it is I'm
guessing you do so this top level goal
is essentially a mission statement it's
the why behind everything that you do
let's say professionally obviously you
know you're a dad you're a husband
you're a friend but just as a writer as
a journalist what is the why that
unifies everything that you do I
understand your question better now and
I am less insulted number one no
disrespect intended number two I dislike
the idea of a mission statement even
more than the top level goal I have to
say really honestly I'm of two minds the
idea of a mission statement sounds
obviously like a good idea right if it's
a well-considered declaration of your
deepest intentions on the other hand my
actual experience with mission
statements is that they are often
institutional BS that they're too soft
to be actionable or there's so obvious
as to be unnecessary it makes me think a
little bit about you know a lot of
companies publish their ethical code and
I can't remember who said it but
somebody smart once wrote about how if a
company decides it needs to write down
their code of ethics they've already
screwed up and the ones that operate
ethically don't actually need to write
down the code of ethics which basically
says you're supposed to not lie cheat
and steal so Stephen I can understand
the cynicism sometimes the rift between
what a company or an organization says
they're going to do and then what they
do is so striking that you kind of wish
they had never said what their ideals
were but look I think it's actually very
helpful to be explicit about your values
because why not add some clarity it's
not a Panacea but would you not agree
that it's better to have a code of
conduct or a set of core principles when
you hire someone for example like they
know what you're all about you know I
know that the good person's answer is
yes Angela you're absolutely right but a
lot of the mission statements I see are
like we help humankind by being forward
thinking individuals with a collective
intention of benevolence so abstract and
so like intractable also it's like a
subset of what we already know as humans
we're supposed to do that's really my
bigger problem with it here's what I
think is a good mission statement is
like a statement of an actual mission
for instance I'm making this up but
here's one from like 1960 eight we're
going to try to send a couple people on
a rocket ship to the moon and get them
there alive have them walk around a
little bit and then get them back to
Earth alive mission accomplished or not
that's what I see as a useful mission
statement there's accountability there's
specificity exactly it's not like
improve humankind maybe you're bristling
at the abstraction and therefore this
feels like meaningless to you you know I
will say this there is an organization I
used to work with that had what I
thought was a lovely mission statement
maybe this is why I'm a little bit down
on it this was for WNYC or New York
Public Radio their mission statement was
I love this it was to make the mind more
Curious the heart more open and the
spirit more joyful through excellent
audio programming that is deeply rooted
in New York city so forget about the
last part about excellent audio
programming to make the mind more
Curious the heart more open the spirit
more Jo I love that like if that was in
a bottle I want to buy it and drink it
but here's the fact that mission
statement was for an organization that
ended up having a lot of organizational
difficulty and this hearkens back a
little bit to moral licensing which is
if I say that I'm doing wonderful things
what's the relationship between that
statement and actually doing wonderful
things and do we actually focus enough
on execution to ensure that we do those
wonderful things as opposed to declare
it that's my issue with mission
statements yeah I can see that but what
I was wondering in that very long
mission statement that started off in
poetry and ended in Pros right with like
audio programming Etc like when you read
it to me by the way I thought you were
going to say what you liked about it was
the last part right because it was
specific and it wasn't so abstract Etc
you're right I'm a bundle of
contradictions aren't I yeah but look I
think the clear answer to this question
is no you do you do not have a top low
goal I will not eat green eggs and ham I
will not eat them samam you know again I
can see how it would be a good idea on
the other hand one reason I thought why
it might not be a good idea is because
if you have something declared or
written down or broadcast as your goal
doesn't that kind of put a crimp on your
ability to evolve and change and
innovate well here's the thing I think
abstraction you know and you were like
ah these things are so vague and what
does it even mean like make the world a
better place the abstraction is good and
bad so you pointed out some of the bad
things about abstraction like it can
kind of mean anything but the good is is
flexibility and if you have a top level
goal like football coach Pete Carroll
who coaches the Seattle Seahawks two
words very simple always compete he uses
the word compete to mean like basically
be your best not to necessarily beat the
opponent it's so abstract and I see how
that could be frustrating like oh what
the heck does this mean but also there's
a reason why these things are so
abstract it is supposed to give a why
for everything that you do and so
there's a tradeoff I think in terms of
abstraction versus specificity I have to
say I love that mission statement always
compete you just like good writing I
think all these on that you like are
like oh that's beautiful maybe but you
know it's exactly what you just said
it's abstract enough to mean almost
anything but it's specific enough you
can always find an explanation for how
it contributes to what you're trying to
do doesn't mean win because sometimes
you can compete as hard as you are
capable of and you're still not going to
win and that doesn't mean that you
failed right for some people it can be
very useful to have a compass which
orients them to what they're doing and
helps them make decisions you know I
have a top level goal and it helps me
give it to us my top level goal is to
use psychological science to help
children Thrive but maybe that goal is
especially helpful to me because I
understand it but maybe when we then ask
the question like how useful is this top
Lev goal for Outsiders maybe it's not as
useful maybe it's even detrimental in
some way for me to pre it around with my
top level goal sign well so I like your
top level goal do you call it a mission
statement or top level goal or is it one
and the same I call it a top level goal
because I think humans have goals that
are hierarchical and we have lots of
low-level goals that are really specific
and concrete and then basically it's
your to-do list right you know what I
got to get done today this week and then
if you ask why like those are goals that
are in service to more abstract longer
term goals maybe things that I'm trying
to get done this year and when you keep
asking why and you can't get any farther
you're like what do you mean why like
that's the whole point of everything
that's when you've gotten to the top and
that's why I call a top level goal but
mission statement works just as well so
here's an interesting example Google
their current mission statement which I
personally find pretty good is as
follows to organize the world's
information and make it universally
accessible and useful what I like about
that is that it's specific and it's not
prachy but just so we know an unofficial
motto of Google but widely disseminated
used to be don't be evil really it was
don't be evil I believe don't be evil
came from way way way back in the
beginning and we should say it lasted up
until I believe it was
2018 when they removed that phrase from
their corporate code of conduct now why
do you think that is well I don't know
if they've ever said why I think they
would be foolish to do so their PR
consulted you would advise against such
a declaration so I'm reading here when
Google was reorganized under their new
parent company alphabet they assumed a
slightly adjusted version of The Motto
and it became do the right thing but
yeah don't be evil was stricken from the
corporate code of conduct in 2018 again
that shows the danger I guess of having
such a statement which is it can and
will be used against you but I think the
first one I read to organize the world's
information that's their actual mission
statement and the other those motos the
two versions are more like they're part
of a corporate code of conduct but you
know your question about this makes me
think about this idea that we wrote
about in one of our books a while ago it
was about the idea of having a moral
compass this is you and levit right
correct we didn't write a book that I
forgot about would that we had but we
haven't yet so the idea of a moral
compass I think again is extremely
appealing we all like to think that we
have learned through our parents and our
communities and the people that we
admire and so on to have a moral compass
a way of navigating our way through the
world but the conclusion that levit and
I came to in this book that we were
writing and Think Like a Freak which was
really trying to help people understand
how to problem solve what we had
advocated was if you're really concerned
about problem solving then you should
put away your moral compass and the
reason is that what a moral compass does
is basically you align yourself to
what's the right or wrong way to think
about a given issue whether it's
fracking or gun control or genetically
engineered food climate change and if
you operate with your moral compass it's
easy to lose track of what the actual
issue is a moral compass can persuade
you that all the answers are obvious
even when they're not it can persuade
you that there's a bright line between
right and wrong even when there isn't
and worse it can persuade you that you
already know everything you need to know
about a subject right you can delude
yourself so in my mind that's my reason
for not wanting to embrace your
perfectly suitable suggestion about the
top level statement if I just forced you
to say something what would you say is a
guiding Philosophy for my work you mean
yeah or you can answer it however you
want I think if I had to have as you're
forcing me to a sort of top level goal
professionally how about every day try
to suck a little bit less which is kind
of like try to be better every day
unless I'm missing something right you
sound totally uninspired by my Topline
goal is there a difference between
sucking less and being better being a
little bit better every day sounds a
little bit back Patty and sanctimonious
whereas trying to suck a little bit less
every day to me sounds a little bit more
motivational
because I'm not looking for praise
actually there is a difference between
trying to be better and trying to suck
less and the difference is in Psychology
anyway we distinguish between approach
motivation and avoidance motivation so
there are two reasons why people strive
and one is because they want to get
better and the other is they want to
fail less so maybe you are running from
sucking or failure I take back my
question because they're not the same
thing I guess I feel that if you're the
kind of person who would even think
about having a top level goal of course
it's to improve and so on but I actually
find that for me personally eliminating
mistakes in other words I hate to say it
accentuating the negative to some degree
or eliminating the negative for me that
is useful because the try to be better
part is meant to be inherent it reminds
me like you know Michelangelo was asked
how do I sculpt a David take away
everything that's not David there you go
not that anybody can really verify that
he said that but maybe it'll come out in
the
factchecking I think some people don't
need a top level goal and that is
because they have their priorities in
order and they don't see any necessity
to be explicit about where they're going
I think maybe the reason why it helped
me is you know everyone's got an inbox
and probably everyone feels like their
inbox is a little more full than they
would like like oh speak here or like
talk to you or like review this document
and if I don't have some way of making
those choices
that is the ultimate why for me it's
like well what am I doing otherwise I
just end up becoming a people pleasing
machine even this podcast that we're
doing together I was like oh well we're
going to be exploring human nature in
ways that hopefully are a little bit
helpful and a little bit engaging and
there'll be some parents and people who
work with kids like teachers and that'll
be helpful and if I didn't have that
connection I wouldn't have done it so
now I feel terrible yeah cuz I'm way
Superior to you morally you're way
Superior to me I'm the opposite of all
the good things that you're promoting no
I'm not using psychological science to
help children Thrive I'm giving parents
terrible ideas about how to destroy
their dreams and to not even bother
having a mission statement no no no
we're both increasing the the metric
tonnage of psychological wisdom even if
by a few
ounces so Angela it sounds like you
believe that a mission statement or top
level goal has real value at least for
many people so even though I'm not a
convert do you feel that most people all
people should do it I'm not going to go
so far as to mandating it for all of
humanity but I will say I think it's
helpful for many people it helped me
I've talked to people you know some on
the younger end 18 19 some quite far
along in life and for a lot of those
people they felt like sitting down with
a pencil and a paper and trying to
actually say what they're all about I
gave them the boundary of like 10 words
or fewer any more than that you're not
even going to remember the darn thing I
think many of those people found it very
helpful not everyone have you noticed
any correlations the kind of people who
are most likely to have mission
statements already are also likely to be
or do X well I think a lot of the people
that I've noticed that have these
mission statements articulated are
actually leaders so what would you say
if a given leader were to say you know
what here's why I don't have a mission
statement mission statements are slogans
that are the province of political
candidates and marketers and if you
think that I and my organization can be
reduced to a mission statement then you
don't understand the way the world
Works wow I would say first of all have
you eaten your s
angry can I make you a sandwich I really
think that's the first thing I would say
but if it weren't the sandwich problem I
guess I would say that almost every
organization I can think of actually
Stephen right literally for profit not
for profit they do have one even
countries have statements I mean the
Declaration of Independence the founding
fathers could have just said like you
know what I mean it's kind of
self-evident right they decided to to
write it down yeah I guess life liberty
in the pursuit of happiness is not a bad
Topline goal I guess it's not all right
I think here's what it boils down you've
persuaded me of this if a Topline goal
or mission statement is well written I'm
okay with it always compete life liberty
pursuit of happiness but once we get
into the you know embrace our
Collective ambiguity to produce
less terrible things in the world by
making our widgets slightly more angular
then I'm probably not so interested I
agree
no stupid questions is part of the fre
economics radio network this episode was
produced by me Rebecca Lee Douglas and
now here's a fact check of today's
conversations in the first half of the
episode Steven says that somebody smart
once wrote that companies that operate
ethically don't need to write down a
code of ethics Steph was likely
referring to the work of Michael
Josephson a former law professor and the
founder of the Josephson Institute of
Ethics Josephs doesn't say that ethical
people don't need ethical codes it's
actually sort of the reverse of that
idea Josephson believes that ethics
codes don't make people ethical and they
don't prevent bad behavior but they can
establish standards of Conduct in areas
not governed by the law so an honesty
framework doesn't prevent dishonesty but
it can establish binding rules of
honesty honestly later on in the episode
Angela tells a popular story about
Michelangelo sculpting David as she
mentioned supposedly the artist was
asked how he created the sculpture and
he responded by saying just take away
everything that's not David Angela was
correct that there is no evidence that
Michelangelo said this versions of the
story can only be traced back to the
19th century in 1876 a weekly paper
called the index printed a humor piece
where the statement was credited to the
famous art critic John Ruskin in the
article the Ruskin character says that
the ancient Greek statue Venus de Milo
was actually a quote pretty poor piece
of work and the simplest thing in the
world because all the artists had to do
was chip off the marble he didn't want
again it's unlikely that Michelangelo or
Ruskin or any other famous artist or
critic ever spoke any version of this
statement but I would personally like to
recommend take away everything that's
not David as a beautifully ambiguous
personal mission statement for any
listeners who want it that's it for the
fact check
no stupid questions is produced by fre
economics radio and Stitcher our staff
includes Allison craiglow Greg rien
James Foster and Karen Wallace our theme
song is and she was by Talking Heads
special thanks to David burn and Warner
Chapel Music if you'd like to listen to
our show ad free subscribe to Stitcher
premium you can also follow us on
Instagram and Twitter at nsq show and on
Facebook at nsq show also if you heard
stepen or Angela refer to something that
you'd like to know more about make sure
to check out our show notes at
freecomic nsq where we link to all the
studies and references that you heard
here today thanks for
listening my kids are like Mom Mom
despite my family text message I'll be
right back you should go take your time
what I'm
recording okay anyway and I I texted you
guys all the stuff for your lunch
details I bought sandwich meat can I
just say that you you didn't text me any
sandwich details I feel left
out Stitcher